<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>TDT - Data Recovery</title><link href="http://tdt.rocks/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://tdt.rocks/feeds/data-recovery.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://tdt.rocks/</id><updated>2017-04-16T03:25:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>Data recovery from a HDD killed by power surge</title><link href="http://tdt.rocks/data_recovery_from_dead_HDD.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-16T03:25:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-04-16T03:25:00+03:00</updated><author><name>James Nzomo</name></author><id>tag:tdt.rocks,2017-04-16:/data_recovery_from_dead_HDD.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A story about how non-backed up data was rescued from oblivion and in the nick of time.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circa ten years ago, before cloud was practically feasible this side of the
sahara, a CPU was assembled for some &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Small_and_medium-sized_enterprises"&gt;SME&lt;/a&gt; with off the shelf parts featuring,
three 500G hard drives:- 2 in raid 1 config, the last with OS ("the OS disk")
to ran custom written software which stashed its inventory and transactions
data into a MySQL DB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the db data dirctory was stored on the mirrored raid pair but circa 4
years back, the OS got reinstalled and the dummy that did that (yours truly)
forgot to set mysql's datadir on the mirrored disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Murphy's law fulfilled&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "OS disk" went kaput!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Finagle's law fulfilled&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "OS disk" went kaput 20 days before the owners were to file TAX returns.
They needed the past year's data ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On inspection, I found that the OS disk was killed by a surge.
The PCB had a charred &lt;a href="http://www.users.on.net/~fzabkar/HDD/TVS_diode_FAQ.html"&gt;TVS diode&lt;/a&gt; and what appear to be a charred
inductors on the power supply side:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="THE DEAD PCB" src="img/data_recovery_from_dead_hdd/pwnt_pcb.jpg" title="PWNT PCB"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fig.1 Top left, burnt TVS diode, top right charred inductors. This clearly wasn't
going to power on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, after rummaging around, I managed to get a similar motherboard off a
similar hard drive down to the model number but differing on Firmware and Board
revision.(100535704 REV C and REV D for the donor and dead pcb respectively)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DONOR &amp;amp; THE DEAD PCB" src="img/data_recovery_from_dead_hdd/donor_n_pwnt_pcb.jpg" title="DONOR &amp;amp; PWNT PCB"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fig.2 Left:- donor pcb, right:- dead pcb.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Recovery attempt numero uno&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with the HDD motherboard swapped, I plugged it in, turned power on and then:-
black screen + blinking underscore. POST was struggling to figure out what
the hell had been pluged into SATA1. There was also a repeated motif of clunking
noise from the now powering on but malfunctioning hard drive.
Multiple retries resulted in a hopeless feels,...but surrender wasn't an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before throwing in the towel and taking it to data recovery specialists (and
explaining why or who would pay circa 100,000 KES {1K USD at the time of this
writing}), I thought it would be WISE to spend afew hours in
data recovery RTFM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Calibrative adaptive information&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as recovery goes, Hard Drives fall into 3 categories:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those recoverable from simple PCB swap,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those that need a BIOS transplanted,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those that have no separate transplantable BIOS. (bios info resides in MCU)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is alot of literature on BIOSes and modern HDDs (google it or see google
juice/references section at bottom) but the long and short of it is the HDD BIOS
stores info that the hard drive's micro controller requires to read the
&lt;a href="http://www.datarecovery.net/articles/hard-drive-system-area.aspx"&gt;System Area which inturn contains calibration and adaptive info unique to the
mechanics of the drive&lt;/a&gt;. This includes manufacturing defect
workarounds and servo specific params. This info is determined and set at the
factory and is probably unique to virtually every modern hard drive that
features a bios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this, you may as well recycle the drive into a paperweight and make
frizbees out of the platters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the three categories. By way of elimination, we already know category 1
is not applicable. The clunking noise was the MCU's quest for access to system
area based on inaccurate BIOS data. Some also say this could have resulted in
a corrupt System Area and irrecoverable data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it was to fall under category 3 (no transplantable BIOS chip data) there
wasn't much I was going to be able to DIY and I would have to trod the 1K USD
path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully that wasn't the case as (after much RTFM) I was able to
locate an 8-pin serial flash memory chip on the dead PCB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Soldering Time!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, a sane trouble-free future lay in that tiny 8-pin ROM chip. The recommended
way would be to transplant that chip to the donor board but that was not without
risk. If during transplant, it gets more heat than the datasheet specs as its max
or if a pin broke, then everything will have come to nothing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I decided to first focus on resurrecting the dead PCB and its less critical
charred components then transplant the BIOS if that was to come to nought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First up, the TVS diode or (Transient Voltage Suppression diode). As the name
suggests, its purpose is to protect circuitry from voltage spikes and probably
incurring damage in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, this TVS gave up the ghost so that the other components may live to
facilitate recovery another day. Thank you dear diode, I will never forget this
sacrifice.
Anyhow, the solution here was to desolder that as it was shorted and diverting
power supply from the rest of the components.
&lt;img alt="DONOR &amp;amp; THE DEAD PCB" src="img/data_recovery_from_dead_hdd/tvs_fix.png" title="TVS FIX"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fig.3 The ressurecting PCB, Left:- Pre TVS diode, Right:- Post TVS diode. (notice the BIOS chip top left)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there was the charred inductors on the power supply side. There were
suggestions on some forums that they could be simply bridged over Which sort
of made sense and so I went ahead and purged the charred few and linked the
respective PCB pads with a dab of solder so that current may flow into the
board and power the rig.
&lt;img alt="DONOR &amp;amp; THE DEAD PCB" src="img/data_recovery_from_dead_hdd/inductor_fix.png" title="IND FIX"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fig.4 The ressurecting PCB Left:- burnt inductors, Right:- One purged and briged.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I checked that both the 12V and 5V rails weren't shorted to ground
and IMHO, the drive was good to go for power up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;RESULT! Recovery WIN!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disk was reunited with the soldered up board and on power-on ALAS! -
it spun up like it was new and the motherboard BIOS even picked it up:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BIOS RECOGNITION WIN" src="img/data_recovery_from_dead_hdd/bios_recognition_win.jpg" title="BIOS RECOGNITION WIN"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fig 5. WIN!. If you went thru the same thing, this image would give you warm fuzzy feeling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I wasn't out of the woods yet. There was the possibility that there could
have been further damage and previous recovery methods could have corrupted
the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus In quick succession:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I rebooted into usb live linux key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rsync-ed /var/lib/mysql out of that failing sucker with the quickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and verified that the that a mysql installation could make sense of the rescued datadir
(which it was)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And RESULT! Disaster had been averted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The end!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Outro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always back up damnit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Resources, Refs &amp;amp; google juice:-&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://hddscan.com/doc/HDD_Tracks_and_Zones.html"&gt;About HDD tracks and zones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.datarecovery.net/articles/hard-drive-system-area.aspx"&gt;An article about the System Area&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hddzone.com/hdd_pcb_bios_rom_chip_nvram.html"&gt;Something about HDD BIOSes and recovery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://eadatahandlers.co.ke/"&gt;When all else fails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yn2eL4o-6Eo"&gt;A vidya on recovery drive categories, from one of the experts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.users.on.net/~fzabkar/HDD/TVS_diode_FAQ.html"&gt;Some articel on TVS Diodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Data Recovery"></category><category term="data recovery"></category><category term="electronics"></category></entry></feed>